Finding aid to the Marie Emilie Gilchrist Papers CA.MS.00017
Smith College Archives
Marie Emilie Gilchrist papers
1906-1990
Smith College Archives
Gilchrist, Marie Emilie, 1893-
CA.MS.00017
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Poet, teacher, editor. Contains poetry and submission records.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marie Emilie Gilchrist Papers were donated to the College Archives in October 1996 by Sarah Watterson Mortimer, Gilchrist's niece.
Arrangement
The papers are organized and labeled according to Gilchrist's own filing system.
Biographical / Historical
Marie Emilie Gilchrist, born January 4, 1893, took an interest in poetry at an early age. She began publishing her work while a student at the Hathaway-Brown School for girls in Cleveland, Ohio. While at Smith, she was active in a number of literary clubs and activities, and published in the Smith College Monthly. Following graduation in 1916, Gilchrist returned to her native Ohio to work at the Cleveland Public Library. She stayed there from 1916-1918, then completed brief stints at an insurance office and the Red Cross. In 1920 she went back to Smith as an English Fellow, receiving her M.A. in 1921. She stayed in Northampton for one year, working at the Hampshire Bookshop, then returned to Cleveland.
In 1926 she resumed work at the Cleveland Public Library, where she remained until 1930. While there she started poetry groups for both children and adults, and held positions in the Stephenson Room for children's literature as well as the adult fiction section. Throughout, Gilchrist wrote poetry and had several pieces published. In 1926 Macmillan released a collection of her poems entitled Wide Pastures. In the summers of 1928 and 1930 she attended the Macdowell Colony for artists in Peterborough, New Hampshire, where she worked on her second book, Writing Poetry, an introduction to poetry for children. Gilchrist also had an interest in the history of the Great Lakes. She produced three children's books related to maritime history in the area, and in 1966 wrote an article for Michigan History on William Ives, a Michigan surveyor (and her uncle).
In 1942, Gilchrist became an associate editor for the Reader's Digest. She retired from the magazine in 1951 but continued to do some editorial work on an hourly basis. It seems likely that Gilchrist wrote poetry until her death in November 1989, but the latest dated poem in this collection is from 1973. Her submission records indicate that she ceased to publish regularly after 1950.
Related Material
80. Class of 1916 Records
Special Collections Department, Cleveland Public Library
Scope and Contents
The Marie Emilie Gilchrist Papers consist of poetry and submission records. The submission records are somewhat irregular. They do not track every poem Gilchrist wrote, nor is there information about every poem she published. The poetry dates from 1906 to 1973 (thinning after 1960), and her biographical material dates from 1934-1990.
Select Bibliography
Books: A Study of Chaucer's Similes. M.A. thesis, Smith College, 1921. Wide Pastures. New York: Macmillan, 1926. Writing Poetry: Suggestions for Young Writers..." Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1932. The Story of the Great Lakes. New York: Harper, 1942. Lithographs by Cornelius Hugh DeWitt. The Story of the United States Coast Guard. Racine, WI: Whitman, 1938. Rolling Along Through the Centuries,with Lucille Ogle. New York: Longmans, Green, 1937. Illustrated by Norbert Lenz. Articles: "William Ives' Huron Mountain Survey, 1846" Michigan History 50:4 (Dec 1966), 323. Poems: "Rag, Tag and Bob-Tail." Smith College Monthly 23, no. 4 (Jan. 1916), 184-191. "Growing Older." Nation 106 (June 22 1918), 735. "Old Eurydamus." Nation 107 (Oct 26 1918), 490. "Summer Rain." Nation 108 (June 21, 1919), 985. "An Uncritical Appreciation." Poet Lore 30:2 (Summer 1919), 304. "Pasturage." Nation 109 (Oct 1919), 498. "En Route: The New England Express." Nation 110 (March 13, 1920), 334. "A Dictionary to Read." Poet Lore 31:2 (Summer 1920), 291. "A Stolen March." Measure: A Journal of Poetry 13 (Mar 1922), 8. "Old Window-Panes." Measure: A Journal of Poetry 13 (Mar 1922), 8. "Bondage." Sunset 48 (Apr 1922), 38. "Dedication." Sunset 49 (Sept 1922), 29. "Answers." Measure: A Journal of Poetry 34 (Dec 1923), 12. "Formula." Measure: A Journal of Poetry 34 (Dec 1923), 13. "Influence." Measure: A Journal of Poetry 34 (Dec 1923), 13 "The Illusionist." Measure: A Journal of Poetry 34 (Dec 1923), 13. "Robert Frost." Current Opinion 76 (Jan 1924), 95. "Encounter." Sunset 52 (Feb 1924), 8. "Poems." Literary Digest 81 (May 17, 1924), 36. "Fundamental." Forum 72:3 (Sept 1924), 338; Current Opinion 77 (Oct 1924), 503. "Flourish." Forum 72:4 (Oct 1924), 526. "Wanted: A Farm." Forum 72:5 (Nov 1924), 697. "Stones in the Road: An Unofficial Epitaph, Reason Speaks." Poetry 26 (Apr/Sept 1925), 319. "Stones in the Road: The Diviner, Beyond, Judgment." Poetry 26 (Apr/Sept 1925), 318. "Weed." Forum 75:4 (Apr 1926), 537. "Lightly. Forum 75:5 (May 1926), 690. "Au Revoir." Forum 76:2 (Aug 1926), 238. "Autumnal." In The Third Book of Modern Verse, edited by Jessie Belle Rittenhouse. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1927. "Wreath for Persephone." In Ring-a-Round: A Collection of Verse for Boys and Girls, edited by Mildred P. Harrington and Corydon Bell. New York: Macmillan, 1930; and in Anthology of Children's Literature, edited by Edna Johnson and Carrie Emma Scott. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1935. "Spring Thunder." Commonweal 13 (March 18, 1931), 549. "Old Timbers." Saturday Review of Literature 10 (Nov 4, 1933), 230. "Strophe: The Wind Rests." Commonweal 19 (Nov 17 1933), 74. "Re-agent." Poetry 43 (Oct-Mar 1933-1934), 197. "By Sailing." Commonweal 19 (Jan 26 1934), 350. "Chance-Fallen Seed." In Book of American Poetry, compiled by Edwin Markham. New York: William H. Wise, 1934. "Springtime Theft." In Verse of Our Day, edited by Margery Gordon. New York: D. Appleton-Century, 1935. "Votive Candle." Commonweal 23 (March 13, 1936), 542. "Apples in New Hampshire." In Poems for a Machine Age-, edited by Horace J. McNeil and Clarence Stratton. New York: McGraw Hill, 1941; and in A Book of Nature Poems, edited by William Cole and Robert Andrew Parker. New York: Viking Press, 1969. "November Letter." Poetry 65 (Oct-Mar 1944-1945), 65. "Warning the Trees." American Scholar 14:3 (Summer 1945), 282. "Saturday in the Country." American Scholar 15:1 (Winter 1945/1946), 64. "Clown's Holiday." Saturday Review of Literature 29 (April 13, 1946), 92. "Spinster." Saturday Review of Literature 29 (June 8, 1946), 18. "Token." Saturday Review of Literature 29 (June 8, 1946), 68. "In Place of Farewell." Yale Review 36 (1946/1947), 277. "Tribute." Saturday Review of Literature 31 (Jan 17, 1948), 32 "Going After." Saturday Review of Literature 31 (Sept 25, 1948), 37.
Gilchrist, Marie Emilie, 1893-; Smith College--Students.
- Biography, 1934-1990 (Box 1893.1, Folder 1)
- "Early Records", 1924-1928 (Box 1893.1, Folder 2)
- Leather Notebook, 1906-1916 (Box 1893.1, Folder 3)
- Leather Notebook, 1916-1924 (Box 1893.1, Folder 4)
- Leather Notebook, 1920s (Box 1893.1, Folder 5)
- "Early [?] Pieces Not Included in Leather Notebook", 1915-1925 (Box 1893.1, Folder 6)
- "[Short?] Poetry Following Leather Notebooks", 1920-1930 (Box 1893.1, Folder 7)
- "1930" (Box 1893.1, Folder 8)
- "1931" (Box 1893.1, Folder 9)
- "1932" (Box 1893.1, Folder 10)
- "1933-1934" (Box 1893.1, Folder 11)
- "Undated: Probably 1930-1935..." (Box 1893.1, Folder 12)
- "1935-1940" (Box 1893.1, Folder 13)
- "1940-1944" (Box 1893.1, Folder 14)
- "1945-1949" (Box 1893.1, Folder 15)
- "1950" (Box 1893.1, Folder 16)
- "1951-1953" (Box 1893.1, Folder 17)
- "1954-1956" (Box 1893.1, Folder 18)
- "1957-1959" (Box 1893.1, Folder 19)
- "1957-1959", 1960-1973 (Box 1893.1, Folder 20)
- "Juvenile", 1935-1936; undated (Box 1893.1, Folder 21)
- "Fragments and Relics", undated (Box 1893.1, Folder 22)
- "Situations", undated (Box 1893.1, Folder 23)
- Michigan History Writings, 1966; undated (Box 1893.1, Folder 25)